have you ever been excited about a new
game only to be disappointed that it
lags I've spent the past six years
creating a game engine and I've been
shocked at the things that can make or
break performance I'll show four simple
optimizations that you can use to make
your games run much quicker and instead
of just talking about them we'll use
them to optimize something that's found
in a lot of games voxal voxal are these
small cubes and this world is composed
of millions of them right now this runs
at 50 frames a second and will increase
it up to 2500 using the first
optimization if we render these voxal
one at a time we would render this map
at one frame a second that's the
opposite of optimization so instead
we'll group them into chunks of 32 all
these voxal now share the same mesh
which lets us render all of them at the
same time we can then combine more
chunks together to create a larger world
this works but it renders very slowly so
let's start optimizing it if we have a
look at the mesh for a chunk and then
zoom in further in into a voxal we can
see that it's composed of 12 triangles
that means the entire world is composed
of 115 million triangles the less
triangles we have the faster our game
will run so let's get rid of some if we
look at these two voxal there's four
triangles between them that will never
be able to see so when we generate the
mesh for this chunk we'll skip the
triangles that are between two voils
this brings our triangle count down
massively to only 1.2 million but we can
reduce it further if we look at this
wall we can see it's composed of voxel
that all have the same metal texture it
looks like a large flat surface but it's
really composed of 1500 triangles we
don't need all these individual
triangles we're better off combining
them together the algorithm for this is
too big to fit on screen but I've put a
link to it in the description we can
also combine them sideways but not until
we've done another optimization in step
four this brings us up to 2500 frames
per second just by reducing the amount
of triangles the next thing we can
optimize is what's stored inside each
triangle
every voxal face has two triangles and
each triangle is composed of three
vertices each of these vertices stores
position and normal vectors and a
texture ID this adds up to 28 bytes per
vertex and for the entire world that's
24 mbes reducing our triangle count
increased our performance and so we're
reducing our memory usage so we'll
compress all this data into one integer
without losing quality to start every
vertex needs a position currently we're
using a vector for this which holds
three FL
these floats are great for standard 3D
models because they can store fractional
values but every triangle in our mesh
lines up to a grid so we can use a bite
instead that's a quarter the size of a
float but we can go even smaller a bite
holds eight bits and can store numbers
up to 255 but our chunks are only 32
voxal wide with seven bits our mesh will
be half the size at up to 127 voxal wide
with six bits our mesh can be up to 63
voxal wide and with 5 bits our mesh can
be up to 31 voxal wide but our chunk
can't fit into that so we'll use six
bits for each of the X Y and Zed
positions we can reduce this further but
not until we've done another
optimization in step three each vertex
also stores a normal Vector which helps
us calculate lighting and other effects
this Vector stores the direction that
each triangle is facing for example here
all the green triangles are facing up
and all the red triangles are facing
left since boxes are cubes there's only
six possible normals they can have so
we'll store the number zero for up one
for down two for right and so on then in
the vertex Shader we can turn this
number back into a vector we can fit
these six directions inside three bits
which is a huge saving lastly each
triangle contains a texture ID which
tells the Shader which texture to apply
we only have 70 unique textures so we
can store this ID using seven bits all
the data we need to render a Vertex can
now fit inside 32 bits which is the size
of one of the floats from the old vector
but the vertex Shader needs to know how
to unpack this data into its separate
components we'll use bit masking for
this the top row here is a mask and
matches the number after the N symbol in
the Shader when we apply this mask to
our vertex data we get a new number with
only the bits that line up with the mask
to unpack the rest of our data we'll
shift it to the right and then apply the
mask again we now have all our data and
can run our Shader as usual but all the
chunks are overlapped in the same
position that's because every vertices
position is now in the range 0 to 32 so
we need to tell each chunk where it is
in the world to do this we'll create a
world position uniform in the vertex
Shader and update it before drawing each
chunk the vertex Shader then adds this
world position to the vertices position
our world now renders correctly and our
memory usage is down to 3.4 mbes this
increased our frames a second up to
4,000 just by reducing the memory usage
but we're still storing more data than
we need to if we look at this wireframe
every voxal face has six vertices and
two of them have the exact same position
storing the same data twice feels like a
waste can we render a voxal face with
only four vertices instead currently
these triangles are rendered
individually which means we need three
vertices for each of them but open G
also lets us render triangles as strips
where each extra vertex builds a new
triangle off the last the problem is
everything gets joined together as one
long strp I thought surely there's a way
to tell open to start a new strip every
four vertices but I couldn't find
anything but I found an even better
solution when games render particles
they use instancing they have a base
particle model and a list of positions
and then open gel draws this model at
all of these positions we didn't have to
create a huge mesh with all these
particles in it and even better each
particle is a triangle strip and they're
not joined together so we'll use
instancing to render our voxels we'll
have a base model for the voxal face
which has only four vertices and then
instead of a list of positions we have a
list of our 32-bit voxal data this voxal
data contains everything we Ed to store
in the mesh but rather than storing it
six times for each face we only have to
store it once but when we render the
world everything is facing up that's
because our base voxal model is facing
up we need to rotate it based on the
face Direction in the vertex Shader if
the face is up we'll lift the model up
if it's facing left we'll rotate it to
the side and the same for the other
direction
but if we look at the world we still
have all these gaps that's because
earlier we combined our triangles
together and we're no longer storing how
long each combined face is we need to
store this length but we don't have room
for another six bits thankfully now that
we're using instancing we can reduce the
size of our position Data before we had
to store positions in the range 0 to 32
which is 33 unique numbers but since our
base voxal model is already one unit
wide we only need to store positions up
to 31 five bits can store exactly 32
unique numbers so we're in luck we also
only need five bits to store the length
because each combined face can be up to
32 voxal long now in the vertex Shader
we can use this length value to stretch
out the base voxal
model this reduced our memory usage by a
factor of six down to 580 Koby that's
because we're only storing one vertex
for each base instead of six also the
vertex Shader only runs four times for
each face because we're using triangle
strips together this increased our
frames a second up to 6500 and the next
optimization will increase it even
further to render this world we're
sending all these commands to the
graphics card this is typical for a game
but we can replace them all with just
one to do this we need to change the way
we store our data right now each chunk
has its own list of instance data in its
own buffer this means we need to ask the
graphics card to render each of them one
at a time instead we can create one huge
buffer and give each chunk a small
portion of it to render a specific part
of this buffer we can use the longest
open gel function ever created the first
two numbers refer to the four vertices
in our base Vox or model the next two
numbers refer to the start and length of
the part of the massive buffer that we
want to draw if we want to render
multiple parts of this buffer we could
repeat this function but now we're back
to multiple draw commands we could just
render the entire combined buffer but
that would render chunks that are
outside our field of view we only want
to render chunks that we can actually
see so what we'll do instead is store
these parameters in a special kind of
buffer called an indirect buffer then we
can use a second longest open gel
function to render them all at the same
time but when we draw them we have that
issue from before where they're all
overlapped that's because we can't use
Shader uniforms anymore to position each
chunk to fix this we'll use another
buffer called a Shader storage buffer
object we can store anything we want in
this buffer and in this case we'll store
the weld position of every chunk we're
trying to draw each of these commands
has a unique ID called GL draw ID this
ID increments for each of our draw
commands so we can use it to select the
right position for each chunk we're now
rendering the entire world with one draw
command which increased our frames a
second up to
12,000 that's because our CPU spends
hardly any time telling the graphics
card what to do and the graphics card
has a huge command it can focus on but
12,000 frames a second isn't the limit
now that we're using one draw command
we've unlocked two bonus optimizations
the first is related to an optimization
that every game uses to ignore triangles
that are on the other side of a model it
works by checking if the points in the
Triangle are going clockwise and if they
aren't the triangle isn't rendered this
speeds up rendering because we're not
wasting time on the triangles that are
facing away from us but the vertex
Shader still has to run every frame to
determine if these triangles are
clockwise or not if we only render the
anticlockwise triangles we can see there
are a lot of them that are facing away
from us this means we're running the
vertex shade for all these triangles and
then just discarding them but we can
stop these triangles from ever reaching
the vertex Shader let's say the play is
standing in this blue Chunk we know
they'll never be able to see the red
triangles in these chunks because
they're facing away from them we also
know they'll never be able to see these
triangles in these chunks so rather than
creating one mesh for each chunk we'll
create six the first mesh only contains
triangles that are facing up the second
only contains triangles that are facing
down and so on we're still only using
one buffer and one draw command but we
have an extra step to only render the
meshes that are facing the player the
vertex Shader is no longer wasting time
on triangles the player can't see which
brings our frames a second up to 14,000
we're now up to the final optimization
earlier I mentioned that we can only
combine faces in One Direction not two
that's because we don't have room to
store another five bits for the combined
horizontal length but we can make room
by deleting the face direction we can do
this because of the Shader storage
buffer object we created before right
now it stores the world position of each
mesh in each chunk but we can also store
the face direction of each mesh this
works because now each chunk has a
separate mesh for each face Direction so
in the vertex Shader we'll replace our
face code with the
ssbo we now have 5 bits free in our
vertex data which is enough to store the
second combined face length by combining
faces in two directions we've reduced
our triangle count down to
79,000 this is now running at 177,000
frames per second which is the highest
it'll go compared to the start we're
using a tiny fraction of our original
memory usage and triangle count this
reduction is the main reason it's
rendering so much faster you can run
these demos yourself and experiment with
the code details are in the video
description there are three more
optimizations that I use to render
massive amounts of terrain which you can
watch in this video on
screen